<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remembraunce for the maintenaunce of the liuynge of ministers and preachers nowe notablye decayed exhibited vnto the right reuerend father in God Thomas Bishop of Elye ...</title>
            <author>Ruddoke, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21435.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23258023</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23258023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26457</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11166)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26457)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remembraunce for the maintenaunce of the liuynge of ministers and preachers nowe notablye decayed exhibited vnto the right reuerend father in God Thomas Bishop of Elye ...</title>
                  <author>Ruddoke, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Wyllyam Seres, dwellynge at Peter Colledge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1551.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: For the maintenaunce of ministers liuinges.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Thomas Ruddoke.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸ D².</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26457:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Remembraunce for the maintenaunce of the liuynge of Miniſters and preachers, nowe notablye decuyed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited vnto the right reuerend father in god Thomas byſhop of Elye, ſyngu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler patron of all good lernynge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. 1551.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Wyllyam Seres, dwellynge at Peter Colledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>TG</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26457:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26457:2"/>
            <head>For the maintenaunce of miniſters liuynge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ffering thys Breife declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto your lordſhip of the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable cauſe whi alfer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mours or owners of Abbey la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds being diſolued ought &amp; ſhold be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tributours &amp; helpers to the liuing of their perſon or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in whoſe pariſh thei be (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe hereof hath hapened betwene me &amp; one of thoſe fermers) Some woulde iudge perchaunce that I were a man gyuen to a certen co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes of liuinge, and thyncke (I ſuppoſe) al wer to litle for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, many woulde bolte oute their grudge ſaienge: this felowe ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth of papiſtrie, and goeth about to ſet vp the kingedome of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. But what ſoeuer any man doth conceaue at the fyrſt hearing
<pb facs="tcp:26457:3"/>
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> title of my declaracion. This wil I proteſt before god &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whol world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſpeake nothig but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> zeale of the auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel &amp; gods true lerninge, which of very neceſſity muſt go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (if god of his wonderfull goodnes ſtaie it not vp) except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudentes and preachers thereof maye be maynteyned wyth honeſt &amp; ſufficyent liuing in the Seruice therof. For by Liuynges all men are enkindled to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudies of good lerning. No man will ronne for nought, and if there be no Reward when he commeth to the markes ende he thincketh his labour loſte in ronninge thither. Wherfore in that that youre lordeſhippes er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt &amp; pure zeale towardes goddes trueth, and the painfull Laborers therin (at my humble ſuet made
<pb facs="tcp:26457:3"/>
vnto you, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> redreſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame matter, willed me to put you in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: I thought it my boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuty ſo to do &amp; ſome thinge to trauayle herein, in ſettinge furth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter more plainly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my penne. Truſting therby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at youre lorde ſhippes handes my ſuet ſhoulde haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better ſucceſſe, &amp; moſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you haue ben alwaies a ſynguler fauorer and preferrer of lerned men, that nowe you would be a patrone to their ſtudies, &amp; to the knowledge and leruinge that ſhall ſprynge after your daies, &amp; to helpe no leſſe to preſerue and continew good lerning emongeſt vs, then you haue heretofore hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to bryng it in. And although there bee Rewardes ſuffycyente and plentyfull inough before god
<pb facs="tcp:26457:4"/>
for all mens paines and ſtudyes in vertue if men wold loke thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwarde and waite there for Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde (as it becometh them to do) yet the nature of man is ſuch, that if he ſee the maintenaunce of hys Liuinge in ſtudie faile (as it were hys breath in hys Raſe to waxe ſhorte) by and by he beginneth to fainte and ſetteth him ſelfe downe idellie, reſting otherwiſe then els he would do. Wherfore an honeſt exhibycion of Liuinge is a greate prouocatyon and ſtaie vnto al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtryous labour and diligence. As longe as a man hathe his due rewarde, his paines is thought the leſſe how many and great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they bee. The rewarde of ſtudye failynge, and the liuinge of miniſtres and preachers not nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhed, is thoccaſion at thys daye
<pb facs="tcp:26457:4"/>
vnto many of ſhrinckynge from their eſtate and vocation and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to ſome other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie to no litle decaie of Chriſte hys faithe and Religion. In ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> where as miniſtres ought accordynge to Paule hys leſſon,<note place="margin">Timot. iiii.</note> giue them ſelues cheifelie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al thinges to exhortacion and doctrine, do cleane contrarie appli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng the in ſelues to the world and forſakinge the ſtudie of the word. The whiche thinge to be true, we maie perceiue and ſe partly by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience manye that haue ſometime labored in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel (not alltogether vnfrutefullie) being not able to purchaſe great benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as it is now a dayes a comon practiſe to do) nor to liue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of their ſtipendes &amp; cures, are driuen to kepe all houſes, exercyſe
<pb facs="tcp:26457:5"/>
the craft of Carpenters, tailors, &amp; other occupations, whych thynge cometh to paſſe thorough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of vncharitable hartes muche choked with couetouſnes, hauing nether zeale towardes the Goſpel, nor the ſetters fourth therof being not wylling to yelde to theyr miny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtres, which dayle &amp; hourely haue labored to bryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to lyghte, that whiche is dewe to them by Scripture, whereby they myght be able to bie bookes, apparel, with other meanes towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des the maintenaunce of their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and Kepe hoſpitalitie for the reliefe of the poore, accordinge to the wyll and commaundement of god.<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii</note> Like as a man goinge on warfare muſte nedes liue of the como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cooſt, &amp; ſo beinge prouided for doeth his deutie a great deale
<pb facs="tcp:26457:5"/>
the better: Euen ſo miniſtres to thentent they may be able, &amp; more willing to do their dueties, ought to haue all thinges neceſſary and ſufficient without care, grudge, or ſuet for the ſame. The maners of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much is to be lamented in theſe dayes, which declareth greatelye theyr vnworthynes of the goſpell thorough the diſſimulacion and vnthanckefull hartes whiche they ſhewe towardes them that haue thouerſyght of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that a great nomber is readier contrarye to the doctryne of the holie Apoſtle, to take, to ſnatche, to catche,<note place="margin">hebr. xiii.</note> and to ſpoile them of that lytle whyche they haue, then to giue that, which in conſciens, they are bounden to giue. This vnthanckefulnes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth to them which vnfainedlie fauoreth goddes true lerninge, a
<pb facs="tcp:26457:6"/>
great euel, ſeyng they ſpoile Chriſt in that they depriue his miniſtres of their liuing. For as woo ſhalbe to the whych ſo largely doth feede the Balaanites y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtres of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they ſhould abounde in al plenteouſnes. Euen ſo they feede Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. x.</note> that nouriſheth his and the ſetters out of his doctrine, &amp; ſhall receue their ful reward at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. What plentifull handes hath ben opened to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> familie and houſhold of Baal? What gorgious houſes what ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous monaſteries hath ben builded for ſuche a couente of Oules, and a herd of ſwyne, being euermore obſcurers of the lighte of the truth? What abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches did thei heape vp what prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce or what degre was he of, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was not benefycyall to them? But in thys world, wherin the brightnes
<pb facs="tcp:26457:6"/>
of gods true light doth moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtlye appere thorough gods prechers (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande of our moſt gracious &amp; noble king Edwarde the ſixte, deliueringe hys people from Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is fro the heuy tradicions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop of Rome, to the excedinge conſolation and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of al people that faithfully coueteth the veryties furtherau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the great diſcomfort of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſireth the hinderance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. What ſcarſite find they? what ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple liuinge do they poſſeſſe? what ſmal rewardes haue they for their good labours? in min opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the erneſt ſettyng oute of thys doctryne is of ſuche a pryce and value, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Englyſhmen had neuer greater cauſe to thancke God and to pray for the gracious proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of theyr mooſt worthye Kynge
<pb facs="tcp:26457:7"/>
and his honorable and lerned cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, then for this matter, and alſo to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more encoraged to declare themſelues louing to the faithful ouerſeers and ſetters out of this doctryne, yea and that much more then they were to the idle lubbers and domme dogges of that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreous Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in times paſte.</p>
            <p>Many at this daie wil fayne to be verie glad to heare the goſpel, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it cometh to paſſe, that eyther they may do a diſpleſure to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of it, or by any pryuy mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hindre him of that whiche is his very deutie, then they ſhew co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to goddes doctryne, wyth al erneſtnes, theyr hypocriſye, which they haue longe noriſhed in their diſſembling hartes both towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the worde and the preachers thereof.<note place="margin">Theſſ. v.</note> No ſmall garde alſo
<pb facs="tcp:26457:7"/>
of ſuche brethren there is that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paſſe either of god or of good ordre, thinckyng themſelues to be parfect maiſters, when in dede they were neuer good ſcollers, whych wil ſay: why ſholde they be chargeable vnto vs? let them la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des as Paule did. Wherin their errour &amp; blindnes doth appeare, in that they thyncke the offyce of preachinge the word, were an idle thinge &amp; not labour: Al though ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ct paule as we read,<note place="margin">actes. xx.</note> dyd get his liuinge wyth his handes, and lefte that whych was dewe, wyth them to whome he had preched, whiche thinge he dyd by libertie and not by neceſſity: Yet he loſt not his ryght of axing hys deutie, which lawfully he might haue had.<note place="margin">ii. Cor. ii.</note> This Apoſtle as he wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſeth Robbed other congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:26457:8"/>
and toke wages of them, that he myght preache the Goſpell fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. ii</note> and to do them ſeruice. Sainct Auguſtine therefore in his booke of workes ſayeth, If they be euangeliſtes, yf they be miniſters, they muſte lyue of the goodes of the faythfull.</p>
            <p>Chriſte promyſed vnto his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles the ſame, &amp; commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſerue of the people thynges neceſſary. Temporalties ought to ſerue as inſtrumentes to ſpirytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al thinges, and ſo that benefyte to be giuen, to the preachers offyce &amp; ayde of his liuynge. The worcke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is worthy his wages, that is: yf they receiuing of the temporall reward be ſpent in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of ſpiritual thinges and not laied vp in coffres but beſtowed in neceſſities and kepynge houſes
<pb facs="tcp:26457:8"/>
of hoſpitalitie not in purchaſynge of great poſſeſſions, or in maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning pompe, pryde, delicate feare, fedinge of houndes, hawkes, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and diſinge, and ſuche lyke euelles, for of ſuche heate what is ſaid in ſcripture:<note place="margin">Iob. xxi.</note> They haue ledde their dayes in vanitie and welth? but ſodenly they go downe to hel.</p>
            <p>Theſe bee they that executeth theyr offyce not as Peter &amp; Paule did, but as Iudas amongeſt the apoſtles, &amp; as Simon Magus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the dyſciples. Theſe (I ſaye) are blinde guides to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſmoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blindeth mens eyes in ſtead of a clere light. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is worthy to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. That they be caſt ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borde, be put out of their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; other to be placed. It is a ſentence alſo moſte pithie to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhe
<pb facs="tcp:26457:9"/>
them, where as the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth:<note place="margin">Timo. iiii.</note> take hede vnto your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ronne in this world that you may receiue a ful reward as the Philippia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s did,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ix.</note> which ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully diſtributed that manyfold grace giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by paule his preching, which walked in their vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not in the pompe of the world, whiche diſtributed, not ſtudied to lay vp and hyde. In like maner the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes that in theſe dayes gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reigneth (I knowe not why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be more worthy to be lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto) the practiſes be ſhamefull that they vſe for the brynging in of money, their mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes are as wide as hel neuer bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g content but groping for occupie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g not of fermes but of townes not of Townes but of hole contreis, in the deſier of encroching they be
<pb facs="tcp:26457:9"/>
ſo roted that they caſt in their her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes how they may defraude euery man of his liuing, or at the leaſt of ſome parte thereof. And alſo wyth what ſpytefull rebukes, taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dringes, thoſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous men deface and put to ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the earneſt ſetters out of the doctrine of Chriſt it is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull, and to muche ſhame to ſpeake of. They would make the miniſtres their ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the preachers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loters &amp; berers with their wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophetes ſpeketh. This is an obſtinat people diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blynge Chyldren,<note place="margin">Eſai. xxx.</note> that refuſeth to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of the Lord. For they ſay vnto the ſeers: ſe not, &amp; to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be clere of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, loke not out right thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for vs, but ſpeke faire wordes vnto vs. The worke of robery is in their handes,<note place="margin">Eſai. lix.</note> in the
<pb facs="tcp:26457:10"/>
waye of crafte and falſehode they go, but the waye of the Lorde they wyl not knowe. But no meruayle it is in dede that the worlde at this day is thus bent towardes the ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and diſpoſers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecretes of God for it hath bene ſo ſence the beginning. Take Abel for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, what ſmall fauour had Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Aaron amonge the cruell Iues,<note place="margin">Gene. iiii. Num. xvi.</note> when they brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of Egipt with many others mo, as Iacob, Ioſeph, Dauid, &amp; Elias. Yea when the wyſe men ſhewed kynge Herode, that the Kynge of the Iewes was borne? he was ſore vexed and al Ieruſalem with him.<note place="margin">Mat. ii.</note> It is no ſmal vexation and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baunce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> riſeth at the true ſounde of goddes worde amongeſt a nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of couetous men and phare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, But verely as when the King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:26457:10"/>
of the papiſtes religion flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed it brought forth riches, and then riches as it were her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpringing vp ſo faſt deuoured the mother. Euen ſo (I feare me) we ſhall fall nowe into a worſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie then that was, thorough neade and neceſſitye, and be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to do as when a mans ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence fayleth him.<note place="margin">Act. iiii.v.</note> And therefore I can not a little alowe the fathers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue church, which ſold al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer they had for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of Chriſtes goſpel, nether was there any amongeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that lacked. Yea &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo which foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Colledges giuing great yere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly rentes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaiyng and vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of learning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mani &amp; diuerſe wel affected me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vertue &amp; knowledge whiche were wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to giue exhibicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb facs="tcp:26457:11"/>
in vniuerſities, and bringe vp pore mennes ſonnes in learninge. And now what ſtreames of teares maye ſeme ſufficiente vnto vs in ſpeakinge of the wonderful decay thereof, which wilbe the very brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in againe of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſnes, &amp; cruelty. And wher as the lawes of this Realme bindeth Clerkes of .C.li. liuinges to finde certen ſcollers in the vniuerſityes, Yet they be ſo ſlouthfull them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, &amp; haue ſo lytle minde to that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not ſtudye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it were as good no lawe to be made and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for then were it no offence to theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience not to do that they knew they were not bound to do. But what is further to be ſayed, ſee you not that euen whereas the late kyng of moſt noble memorye Kinge Henry the eyght hath buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:26457:11"/>
colledges, and giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great yere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye ſtipendes for the maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of pore mens children to learning, whiche were not able of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſo to ſet them forwarde. Howe ſhamefullye euen ſtraight wayes thys thynge is abuſed, emongeſte men of knowledge, and of a hygh profeſſion of godes worde, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye gentleman as he can beſte make hys frende bringeth in hys Sonne thyther, and kepeth hym there, with the liuing ordeined for the pore mans ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, wher he muſt be daintelye brought vp, with as lytle applyeng of lerninge as may be, ſauing for his breking a while to ſe the maner of the vniuerſitye, and ſo prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a time there almoſt in idlenes. Where the pore ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler is driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his ſtudye, &amp; would wyth all his harte refuſe no pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:26457:12"/>
to come to knowledge (howe hard ſo euer they were) if he had y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to put in hys bealye and laye on hys backe to kepe him there, that the gentlemans ſonne agaynſte all reaſon and conſciens in myne opynyon kepethe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, Yea &amp; many of them minding to departe from the vniuerſitie, a lytle before procureth a lyke chapman to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for hys rome. So that the worlde is ſo farre runne in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes at thys day by couetouſnes in catchyng all and departyng from nothyng that oneleſſe other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſyon be founde or thys that is alredy made be better loked vnto, it wyll come to paſſe that the way whyche is thought to expel papy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrye longe rooted amongeſte the people, wilbe the redreſt and moſt ſtrongeſt meane to brynge it in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne,
<pb facs="tcp:26457:12"/>
in that the mayntenaunce of ſtudentes doth wante, whereby it is impoſſyble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good learninge ſhulde ſprynge. What is he that hath traueled in ſtudy theſe many yeres y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at this preſent can receiue the rewarde of hys ſtudye. That is, other a benefyce or lyke Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng at a nombre of handes, but it ſhal be other ſold, or equally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided betwene the taker and the giuer, or els it paſſeth ouer to ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple ſir Iohn, which can ſcaſe read an homelie, and in dede loketh for no further, if that he can brynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> well to paſſe. And ſo the Benefyce beinge worth .xl.li. by yere, he ſhal haue .xx. nobles being a perſonne in name, and a verye ſeruaunte in dede. Yea, and ſome pretende (if they myght be ſuffred to bryng it to paſſe) to vnite their patronages
<pb facs="tcp:26457:13"/>
ſhortli to their inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Wold not thys brynge in a great pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye thinke you? Woulde not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty ſeke agayne after olde ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſh marchandiſe thyncke you? I feare it muche. O caſe moſte la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, &amp; men moſte vnworthy ſuch patronages. With what face ſhall ſuche loke at the latter daye before the iudgemente ſeate of the greate iudge Chriſte Ieſus? Or ſuch of whom the ſcripture ſayth: Thenemie hath put hys hande to al thyngs to him deſierable,<note place="margin">Lamen. i.</note> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hath a certaine people Lawles entrynge into his ſanctuarie, that neither them ſelues kepe the lawe of God, nor ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come in that can teache other.</p>
            <p>Therfore God by his Prophet Oſee ſayeth:<note place="margin">Oſias. iiii.</note> For that thou haſte put away the knowledge of gods
<pb facs="tcp:26457:13"/>
wyll, I wyll put the away, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalt vſe no prieſthode to me, how wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> anſwere God, O ignorant prieſte, when thou ſhalte come to thy rekening, it is to be fered thou wilt ſtand dombe for lacke of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, and for confuſion of thyne owne conſcience. Thou I ſay, and thy maiſter the patrone placynge the not as a heard, but as an hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, both you twayne (I ſaye,) ſhall fall into thys moſte horrible ſentence.<note place="margin">Mat. xxii.</note> Take them and bynde them hande and fote. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And what is to be thought here in of wycked inproperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, whych haue plucked from ſtudentes lawefull liuynges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge ordeyned for the Preachers of the Goſpell. Manye Godlye men ſurely haue preached and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly herein their learnyng
<pb facs="tcp:26457:14"/>
and gods trueth to the vtter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the ſame, to whome I ſubſcrybe wyth all my harte, wyſhing of god mooſt hartelye a redreſſe to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the ſame, or at the leaſte it wyll pleaſe the kynges maieſtie hys mooſt excellent and gracious goodnes, hauing reſpect to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of hys prechers within hys Realme, woulde not here after graunt or ſuffer any ſuch licences of improperacions to paſſe, and I would wyſhe that the byſhops would not gyue theyr good wyl &amp; conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therunto for obſcience ſake, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at the leaſt we might reſerue vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the poſterity of ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal folow vs, no ſmal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler or fewer rewardes for theyr ſtudye then we haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. What ſhal we ſay vnto mam of the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:26457:14"/>
of religion (as they called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) whyche were exempted from pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge or contrybuting any thinge to the mayntenaunce of miniſtres and preachers, by reaſon wherof, the owners and fermours at this daie claime to pay nothynge, and yet to haue the miniſtres as much bounde to them as to the reſte of the pariſh,<note place="margin">i. Tim. v.</note> I wolde haue the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> note wel ſaint Paules ſaieng herein: The elders that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth well are worthye double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Moſte ſpecially they which labour in the word and techyng. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture ſaith. Thou ſhalt not moſell the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne.<note place="margin">Deu. xxv. i. Tim, v.</note> Haue they any Auctorytie to condemme this? Or gaue they any liberty by this to famiſh the Oxe, or to ſcant the Oxe of his meat? No forſoth.
<pb facs="tcp:26457:15"/>
for thou ſhalt not (ſayth the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) caſte anye Moſell vpon hys mouth. And what if thoſe dul &amp; fat oxen whyche were eſtalled in their Abbayes, grated vpon the people in this (as in all thinges they lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed importible burdens vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them) claymynge to fede and liue vpon theyr goodes. Were thoſe thynke you the oxen that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture here ſpeaketh of? Or if they were, is there any ſucceſſion or inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into the office of thoſe Oxen? No verelye, for in that ſayinge of the ſcripture, there is a further thinge then appeareth, for it is not ment but of the ſpiritual Oxe, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, the ſpirituall treader oute of the corne of the lyuyſhe worde of god vnto his people. Such trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Chriſt byddeth vs deſire our <note place="margin">Mat. x,</note>heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father to ſend into his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt.
<pb facs="tcp:26457:15"/>
But thoſe Abbey Oxen were ſcholemaſters of ceremonies, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s traditions, ſuperſticion, &amp; finallye of all ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Wherfore if you be not lyke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe landes now you do poſſes (as if you were, you were vnworthye of any thynge) if you haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of preachinge (as it is manifeſte you haue not) whych way then ſhold you claime to lyue vppon that portion of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng whych parteyneth to the ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en that drawe in Gods ploughe? Mary you wyl peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture giue place to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifeſtnes of Goddes ſcripture in thys behalfe (as you muſt nedes) and you wyll brynge me in a reaſon for youre purpoſe on this wyſe. We haue purchaſed theſe fredomes and exemptions of payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of Tythes of the kinges maieſtie, hys moſte noble proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitours,
<pb facs="tcp:26457:16"/>
and we haue them grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs in as ample wyſe as the monaſteryes euer had. Whye ſhuld then our liberties therof be taken from vs? Well, marke I praye you a greate ſorte of you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyth holde theſe duties, were not your monaſteries pariſhes by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues? And neuer chargeable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vicars or ꝑſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of any pariſh? it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be denied, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl I improue your reaſon on this wiſe. The pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiaritie of your fredomes (is cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne) was in reſpect of your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhes. Your pariſhes be extinct, ergo your fredome is extinct. Whi ſhould you then ſeyng your pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes be dyſſolued aſſociate youre ſelues to the floke of the herdma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and contrarye to ſainte Paules leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſuffer him to eate of your mylke?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26457:16"/>Peraduenture agayne you wyll ſtande in this, and ſay generally,<note place="margin">Cor. ix.</note> That no man by the ſcripture of god is bounde to paye any tithes of dutie to their Curates as thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which they mai not pretermit, but ſuche as they are able to ſpare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the meſure of theyr owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and as they ſee theym do their duties. Pithely ſpoken, and as much I think as is vſed to be ſayde for you, wherin thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matters you comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The paymente of tithes whether they be of neceſſitie and by the lawe of god or no? Then whither youre abilitie ought to be loked vpon in the paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therof (As for your conſcience I wil not ſpeake of it, for it is no queſtion whither you ſhold pay any if they were meſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by your conſcience.) Laſt of al
<pb facs="tcp:26457:17"/>
whither the not doinge of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters duties as you loke for, be a ſuffycient cauſe for you to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydge them of their tithes. To proue that the tythes be of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bookes of Exodus, Leuiticus, Numeri, Deutro, Malach, Eccleſiaſticus, do teach the plainely, the autoritie is good my voucher is true.</p>
            <p>Yea mary you ſaye, but the old lawe was but a figure, and the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures be aboliſhed and vaniſhed awaye with the lawe.</p>
            <p>You runne verye faſt awaye, but ſtay a little, &amp; herken what Chriſt ſayeth: Thynke not that I come to deſtroy the law, or the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.<note place="margin">Mat. v.</note> No, I am not come to deſtroy but to fulfyll. Then marcke that Chriſte is come to fulfyll, whyche is to approue, to alowe, &amp; to make
<pb facs="tcp:26457:17"/>
good the ſayinges of the law and the Prophetes, and not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them and take them cleare awai as ſhadowes. For although Chriſtes commyng aboliſhed and did dryue away (beinge hym ſelfe the perfection and the ende of the lawe) al figures and ſygnes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whyche hys moſte acceptable commynge dyd appeare. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the lawe which perteineth to erudicion, example, and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion neceſſary amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, he did not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne or take away, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth Luk. ii. in this ſame point, wher he rebuketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſes for great matters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they left vndone,<note place="margin">Luk. ii.</note> yet for their due payinge of tithes whyche they hyghlye eſtemed of mynte, and rewe, he rebuked them not, but rather alowed, he checked them for their peruerſitie, he repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hended
<pb facs="tcp:26457:18"/>
not there diligence of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. As to the abilitie of payers of tithes whither it be, to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paiyng therof? Yf there abilitie be ſufficyente, they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded as you ſe, and muſte nedes paye. Yf they be poore and indy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, then are the tithes, although they be, receiued by the miniſtres parte alſo of there porcion of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng, and oughte to be diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and larged oute by the myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to the mayntenaunce &amp; helpe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore widowes &amp; fatherleſſe or what ſo euer they be, wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture dothe not onely conſent, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auctoryte of many aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Doctors, for in dede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goods of the churche be the goodes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore. But now a daies y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt nomber of them be but ſymple diſtributers, for they ſcarſe can be
<pb facs="tcp:26457:18"/>
truſted for meate and dryncke to put in there owne bellies. Then whether the not doinge of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hys dutie as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people loke for be a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe to abridge them of there dueties or no? All thoughe in dede I woulde haue no miniſter thincke that he hathe done his parte ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ynough in that behalfe, but that he ſhuld traueile and ſpende his time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually inſtructing, enformyng, and exerciſinge hys flocke in the knowledge &amp; lerninge of goddes holy Goſpell. Yet if he haue not ſuche a gifte and talente of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge or vtteraunce giuen him as other haue, whereby he maye ſatiſfye the deſyer of a great ſorte for as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle ſaith: The giftes of the holy goſte be diuers, and euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath receiued according
<pb facs="tcp:26457:19"/>
to the meſure of the gifte of God yet he ought not therfore to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyſed, or to haue his liuing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, ſpetially if he trauell wyth all hys diligence and wyth his beſt power. To do more, then the gyfte whyche they haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued doth extende vnto, they are not bidden, for ſainct Peter by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them.<note place="margin">i. Peter. v.</note> See that you fede ſo muche as lyeth in you. And I woulde not haue them in dede do one iote leſſe thoroughe Idelenes or entanglinge in other neceſſary matters for there is a great waite hangeth vpon there heades, the bloude of the ſhepe ſhalbe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the ſhepherdes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it manifeſte that their dutyes hange not vpon your expectacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Eze. xxxiii.</note> but vpon their owne diligence.</p>
            <p>And nowe to theſe Abbey owners
<pb facs="tcp:26457:19"/>
agayne I ſay, if they wil be of the congregation, they muſte do as the congregation doth. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is bounde to miniſter vnto their teachers &amp; ouerſeers, ergo they be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to do likewiſe. But although they coulde fetche them a good title from the law of man (whych they wold fayne find oute) to diſcharge them ſelues of diſtributing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prechers liuing, ſhall Chriſte and all the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of hys ſcripture woorke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing herein to enforme there con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience? Chriſt ſaieth: The work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is worthy his wages,<note place="margin">Math. x</note> how da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſte thou then kepe it from him? Sainct Paule ſaieth: He that is taught in the worde ought to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto him that teacheth him in all good thinges. Who is then exempted? Who is diſcharged? or
<pb facs="tcp:26457:20"/>
what is it thou ſhuldeſt grudge to giue him? And further he ſaithe that in hope he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ploweth ſhulde plow, &amp; he that threſheth in hope, ſhoulde be partaker of hys hope. And that it maye be plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued what the apoſtle meaneth by it, ſtreight waie he ſaith: Yf we haue ſowen ſpiritual thinges vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you, is it a great matter if that we reape youre carnall thinges? Doo not you know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they whiche laboure in holye thinges, liue of the ſame? Euen ſo the Lord hath ordeined y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they whych preach the Goſpel, ſhuld lyue of the Goſpel. Manifeſte it is to euery one that vnfaynedlye ſearcheth the worde of GOD, how of dutye the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ought to bringe in vnto god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des preachers thynges ſufficient. For though theyr office be hyghe
<pb facs="tcp:26457:20"/>
and heauenlye, yet God doeth not vſe communely to ſende hys aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels thence to brynge them meate and money. But hys wyll is that they to whom the worde &amp; ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes are m niſtred, whether they be owners of monaſteries or far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, ſhould plentifully and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye wyllyngely rewarde them for theyr laboure. And therefore, he openeth the wyndowes of heauen vnto them, and poureth out vnto them a bleſſynge with plentuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of corne, fruite,<note place="margin">Malach. iii.</note> and manifold encreaſe.</p>
            <p>And herein a godlier ordre ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not otherwyſe be deuiſed for theyr ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt rewardes,<note place="margin">Exod. xxii. Leui. xxvii. Nu. xviii. Deu. xii. Malach. iii. Eccle. vii.</note> then almighty god ordeyned and appointed in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes tyme, that the tenthe parte of all that came oute of the grounde ſhould be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the Leuites
<pb facs="tcp:26457:21"/>
and Prieſtes,<note place="margin">Eccle. vii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. iii.</note> and that wythoute fraude and of the beſt. They that wyl may reade, none was then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted, and why ſhould any now be exempted, but rather be bound more by the law of GOD to giue after the rule of charitie.</p>
            <p>The miniſters of the churche of God hath a ſeuerall office from al other, and therfore God wyll that a ſeuerall prouiſion be made for them, or els it ſhould be a greate hinderaunce to the preachynge of the goſpell, in that they ſhould of neceſſitie be driuen to get their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng by ſome other facultie.</p>
            <p>Prouiſion was made by Gods appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for the prieſtes of the olde lawe and ſhadowes, &amp; ſhall not the miniſters of the Goſpel be muche more prouided for, as wel of the goodes of owners and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
<pb facs="tcp:26457:21"/>
of diſſolued Abbey landes as of other, ſeynge they preach not ſhadowes, but the trueth it ſelfe: both to thoſe fermers and owners as to all other? The dygger, the Clayer, the Carpenter, the Tyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man loketh for hys wages, and is ſure to haue it, much more he that laboreth in the harueſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, oughte to be ſure of hys wages, and to be payed with a good wyl, ſo muche as the ſoule is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodye.</p>
            <p>Saint Paule that elect veſſel of GOD ſayeth:<note place="margin">Cor. ix.</note> that thoſe that preache the Goſpell, ſhoulde lyue therby, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is of there goods to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is preached. But for as muche as the hartes and ſtomakes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſo ſoore corrupte and defiled with diſſimulation and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion not only agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prechers,
<pb facs="tcp:26457:22"/>
but alſo (as appeareth by their dedes) againſt the verites furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, to haue a poſitiue lawe is verye neceſſarye. That where as the worde of God that ſpirituall ſworde can not prouoke theim to that thynge whyche is good, yet that the feare of the temporall ſwerde myght compell theym to do well. I meane the owners and farmers of Abbey grainges whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be taught and miniſtred vnto wyth other, yet wyl helpe nothing vnto the lyuynge of their Curate wyth other.</p>
            <p>For as it hath bene alwayes the ordeynaunce of God to haue ſpirituall paſtours to enſtruct the people wyth hys worde: euen ſo by the ſame ordinaunces, kynges and chyefe rulers are ordeined to defende the ſame with the ſwerd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26457:22"/>And as abundaunce of riches and poſſeſſions can not helpe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather cauſeth him to forget hym ſelfe, Yea oftentimes oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth hym as too greate a waighte doth a Shyppe. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo pouertie and muche beggerlynes bringeth a man oftentimes into diſdayne, and maketh him to be forgotten. And as the mans perſonne is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, ſo is his doctrine vilipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſet at nought.</p>
            <p>The very beginning of al errour and miſorder in this worlde as the lerned man) ſaith, is the depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of iudgementes when as thynges haue not theyr due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes.</p>
            <p>And ſurely lyke as that family and houſholde can not ſtand and endure where as enuy &amp; diſdayne one towardes another raygneth,</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26457:23"/>Euen ſo I feare me, if that the ſuppreſſyon of lyuynges of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and preachers be winked at. Yea if they be not maynteined w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the rule of hys doctrine that iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth euerye thynge wyth ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, not only the numbre ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhal decaye, but the byſhoppes theym ſelues in not prouydynge and ſpeakynge for them, ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be a iuſte puniſhment of God, haue theyr lyuynges ſo taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, that at the length they ſhall be caſte into lyke pouertie.</p>
            <p>The whych if it ſhould ſo come to paſſe, howe lyttle their worde and preachynge ſhould be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? Howe greate confuſion alſo otherwyſe ſhoulde enſue, euerye man wythin hym ſelfe playnelye perceyueth, and daylye more and more maye vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. To preach
<pb facs="tcp:26457:23"/>
Chriſtes Goſpell ſincerely (to the byſhoppes theyr lyuynges was geuen,) and alſo not to forgette in their abundaunce, the oppreſſed and neady, but to haue a diligent eye vnto them, eſpeciallye whyche are of the houſholde of fayeth: if they be neuer ſo politykelye occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, and beare neuer ſo greate a zeale to the commune wealth. Yet if they ſeke not fyrſte therein, the kyngedome of GOD,<note place="margin">Mat. vi.</note> and the maintenaunce of hys holye worde and ſeruice, all is but vayne what ſoeuer they do.</p>
            <p>Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſeduced nor ſnared w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dignitie &amp; promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this world, nor deſire to folow ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whiche thynge whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome men haue coueted, they haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; forgotten theyr ryghte vocation, applyinge them ſelues to thinges
<pb facs="tcp:26457:24"/>
not neceſſarye. But let them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther folow quietnes in ſtudi of ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, a thinge paſſinge al wordly treſures (if a man haue ſufficient to the maintenaunce thereof,) and take no hede what the moſt parte doeth, or what is moſt profitable for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purſe, but what is to be done riches &amp; dignities if they come not by vertu thei are euel, if thei come by vertue, then is vertue better then they, &amp; they not muche to be regarded. Yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be called a parfect &amp; a whole man lackyng any partes or members belonging to man, ſo is it no parfect co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth (except it be maintened with all eſtates degrees and ſortes of people) expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient and neceſſary to the ſame.</p>
            <p>Therefore lyke as a man is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially gouerned by reaſon, whych
<pb facs="tcp:26457:24"/>
defendeth and loketh vnto all the members of the bodye, euen ſo a Realme doeth floryſhe thorough a vertuous and a louing kyng to wardes his ſubiectes, by execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting true iuſtice that the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be mai dwel by the wolfe, the poore by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riche. And as al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other partes of man as his head, fete and handes wyth the reaſt ſtandeth nede eche of other and all to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the bodi: So al degrees of peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple are to the vp holdinge &amp; ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the comon welthe as magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrates artificers with ſuch other</p>
            <p>Agayne, as the body canne not well gouerne it ſelfe wythoute the principal part of the eye, but ſhal wander, not knowynge whyther to go: So the people beynge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of theyr eyes, which are the preachers of Goddes worde, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:26457:25"/>
fall into all errours and blindnes of the ſoule, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let them none otherwyſe thynke, but that al ſhal go againſte theym, what ſo euer good thynge they take in hande. For he that knoweth not God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghte, that loueth hym not, that dreadeth and feareth not hys ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible threatenynges, hym wyll he gyue vp to folow his owne blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, there is no doubte,<note place="margin">Rom. i.</note> as he hath done vnto them, in whom the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye of Eſay at thys day is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified. Of theſe he loked for equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but ſe,<note place="margin">Eſaie. v.</note> there is wrong for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes. Loe it is but miſerie. &amp;c And amongeſt vs where townes and villages were fruitfullie oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied with huſbandrye, by wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked oppreſſion loe they be fallen downe and turned into paſtures, or els one or two men holdeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:26457:25"/>
al and let their neyghbours haue none. Wel let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be meri a while. The darcknes of Hell ſhall fall vpon ſuche at the laſte, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not doubte. For it is vnpoſſible for a curſed extorcioner or a couetouſe idolater that truſteth in the dead God of his riches &amp; ſacrifieth ſo vnto him, to ſe the light of heuen. Sainct Paule chargeth you that are riche in thys worlde, that you be not hygh minded, nor truſt in vncerten riches, but in the lyuing god (which giueth vs abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all thinges to enioye them) that you do good worckes,<note place="margin">i. Tim. vi.</note> that you be redie to giue, &amp; glade to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, laiynge vp in ſtore for your ſelues a good foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the tyme to come, that you maye obteyne eternall life. Take good hede to your ſelues I ſay againe,
<pb facs="tcp:26457:26"/>
Marke wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as they were obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the lawes of God, floriſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al plentifulnes. But after they fel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> litle regarding the inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; teachynges geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god by Moſes &amp; Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their guides, they were baniſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al theyr wealth and ſore ſcourged of God, &amp; brought into captiuitie.</p>
            <p>Wherfore let vs diligently harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God. Let vs erneſtly regard the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leſt we taſt of the myſfortunes that fell vpon the Iſraelites. Let vs regard the prechers thereof,<note place="margin">Ebrue. xiii.</note> and maynteine goddes meſſengers amongeſt vs that watche for our ſoules eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they that muſt giue accomptes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may do it wyth ioye and not with grefe, and they ſhall teache vs to walk ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhal not ſlide.
<pb facs="tcp:26457:26"/>
Let vs cheriſh their ſtudies if thei be neceſſarye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres amonge vs, let vs prouide y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of them decay not, but pray that it may be multiplied. Al you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be patrones of learning in this realme, now ſet to your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> learning ſeke her not an other region to dwel in, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled wyth pouertie. But em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace her amongeſt your ſelues, interteine her, and reteine her dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently wyth all the prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you can make, It is nowe time and that wyth ſpede: for couetouſnes, ambycyon, and pryde, ſtandeth in wait for their rewardes, and thur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteth at her very ſore to dryue her awaye. In whoſe cauſe, I at this tyme all th nges (ryght honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lord) wayed and conſidered, &amp; accordynge to gods holye worde ſincerly and purelie diſcuſſed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng
<pb facs="tcp:26457:27"/>
not ſo muche an eye to mine owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditye &amp; profit of many other, yea, and to the horrible inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie of al true chriſtians (if remedy be not found in this behalfe) do here hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech your Lordſhip, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as you haue ben a ſinguler patrone of al good and vertuous ſtudies, a defender of the truth, a mayntener of poore mens cauſes, that nowe you wyll proſecute and go forwarde to the lande of God, and beautifying of learned ſtudyes to your power, in the redreſſinge &amp; expulſyng of all theſe enormities before reherſed, nowe moſt manifeſtly rayninge in thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, for Gods ſake, and hys holy wordes ſake.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <byline>By your Lordſhips moſt bounden Thomas Ruddoke.</byline>
            <pb facs="tcp:26457:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
